NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services Files. 6174/003
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education – Hurd Report See also: State Aid See also: Hurd City Grants See also: Levittown v. Nyquist, 1981 (Box 59, Folder 18)
  Final report, "An Examination and Recommendations Concerning the Problems of City School Districts Subject to the Constitutional Tax Limitations," Hurd Study Group, Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education, July 1981; incidental correspondence.
- Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education (folder 1), 1980 (Box 59, Folder 19)
  Chapter drafts of report by special NYS task force; correspondence
- Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education (folder 2), 1979-1980 (Box 59, Folder 20)
  "Summary Research Findings and Policy Alternatives: A Second Interim Report," September 1980; draft reports by the Education Commission of the States: "A Regional Analysis of School Finance in New York State," June 9, 1979, "Preliminary Results on Predicted Salaries and a Cost-of-Education Index for New York State," "Regional Cost Differences: An Analysis Using the Cost-of- Education Index," "A Regional Analysis of School Finance in New York State: Additional Research," "An Interpretation of the Results of the Statistical Analysis for Teachers' Salaries," July 27, 1979; memo, Summary of Fiscal Capacity Issues, December 5, 1980; related materials
- Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education (folder 3), 1979-1980 (Box 59, Folder 21)
  Revised draft of interim report, April 24, 1979; staff summary of interim report; conference survey on school finance questions; report, "Regional Differences in Costs: A Study by the Sub-Committee of the Legislative Committee of the NYS Council of School District Administrators," September 1978; other cost- analysis papers by Education Commission of the States
- Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education (folder 4), 1980 (Box 59, Folder 22)
  Final report, "Study of Adjustments of NYS School Aid Formula to Take Account of Municipal Overburdens," by Maxwell School, Syracuse University, May 1980; paper on municipal overburden, by Education Commission for the States, May 1980; The Search for Equity: Interim Report of the Special Task Force
- Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education (folder 5), 1981 (Box 60, Folder 1)
  Meeting agenda, April 15; background papers: "Implementing the Urban Mandate of Levittown v. Nyquist: An Analysis of Alternative Approaches to Compensating for Municipal Overburden in the New York State Aid Formula," an interim report prepared for the NYC Board of Education and the United Federation of Teachers School Finance Reform Project, by Educational Testing Service, March 6, 1981; simulation results, "The Contributions That Could be Made by the School Finance Formula toward the Elimination of the Hurd City Problem"; paper by UFT, "On State Support of Teacher Centers"; draft report, "An Examination and Recommendations Concerning the Problems of City School Districts Subject to the Constitutional Tax Limitation," by Hurd Study Group of Special Task Force, April 15, 1981
- Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education (folder 6), 1979-1980 (Box 60, Folder 2)
  Final report, "Study of Adjustments of NYS School Aid Formula to Take Account of Municipal Overburdens," by Maxwell School, Syracuse University, May 1980; research report by Education Commission of the States, "Alternative Measures of School District Fiscal Capacity," October 24, 1979; background papers by rural study group, including draft by Cornell University College of Agriculture faculty members; meeting agendas; handwritten notes
- Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education (folder 7), 1979-1980 (Box 60, Folder 3)
  Paper by Education Commission of the States re education cost index; related materials
- Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education (folder 8), 1979-1980 (Box 60, Folder 4)
  Bound copy, Research Findings and Policy Alternatives: A Second Interim Report," NYS Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education, September 1980; "Potential Effects of the Overburden Argument on the Funding of Rural Schools," interim report to the NYS Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education, by faculty of NYS College of Agriculture and Life Sciences at Cornell University; related materials
- Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education (folder 9), 1979-1980 (Box 60, Folder 5)
  Draft second interim report; working document for final policy options; related materials
- Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education – Second Interim Report June 1980 (Box 60, Folder 6)
  Second Interim Report, with cover letter to NYS governor Hugh Carey
- Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education – Retreat Support Document Impacts and Rationales, 1981 (Box 60, Folder 7)
  November 30, 1981. Final draft, with cover letter from NYS Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education, December 2, 1981
- NYS Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education September 1980 – Research Findings and Policy Alternatives: A Second Interim Report (Box 60, Folder 8)
  Final printed publication
- Use of Income in Adjusting the Measure of School District Wealth for Purposes of State Aid October 1981 (Box 60, Folder 9)
  NYSUT report
- Estimated Effects of an Expanded Tax Base Approach for 1982-83 November 1981 (Box 60, Folder 10)
  Report prepared by the NYS Education Department for the NYS Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education
- Income: NYSUT Position, 1979 (Box 60, Folder 11)
  c. 1979. Statement by NYSUT president Thomas Y. Hobart re state aid formula in light of Levittown decision
- Income: Fact Sheet, 1979 (Box 60, Folder 12)
  c. 1979. Fact sheet from NYSUT president Hobart re complexity of calculating state aid based on wealth
- County Wealth Sharing, 1979 (Box 60, Folder 13)
  c. 1979. Statement by NYSUT president Hobart against endorsing wealth sharing in school aid formulas
- Responses of Hobart to the Survey of the Special Task Force September 1981 (Box 60, Folder 14)
  NYSUT publication
- The Search for Equity: Interim Report of the Special Task Force May 1979 (Box 60, Folder 15)
  60
- Speeches, 1977-1985 (Box 60, Folder 16)
  Text of testimony by NYSUT president Thomas Y. Hobart and others to state legislative committees re educational issues
- Speeches – Background, 1977-1985 (Box 60, Folder 17)
  "Update of State Reform Initiatives in Education," prepared by AFT Educational Issues Dept., January 22, 1985; "Proposal to the Legislature on the Governance and Funding of the City University of New York," April 19, 1979; summary of findings of 17th annual Gallup Poll of public attitudes toward public schools
- Staff Differentiation (folder 1), 1970-1971 (Box 60, Folder 18)
  Final report, "A Functional Analysis of Differentiated Staffing Projects Funded by U.S.O.E. [Office of Education]," vol. II, Graduate School of Education, University of California
- Staff Differentiation (folder 2), 1970 (Box 60, Folder 19)
  Report, "Differentiated Staffing in the Cherry Creek Schools of Metropolitan Denver, Colorado," vols. I & II, August 1970
- Staff Differentiation (folder 3), 1970-1971 (Box 60, Folder 20)
  "How to Negotiate a Differentiated Teaching Staff," by Dr. Fenwick W. English, for the Canadian Teachers' Association, November 1972; "How to Build a Model of Staff Differentiation," by Dr. Fenwick W. English, for the Arizona-Mesa Differentiated Staffing Consortium; other volumes of reports, papers
- Staff Differentiation (folder 4), 1970 (Box 61, Folder 1)
  Volumes of reports and papers for New York City and other school districts, many written by Dr. Fenwick W. English
- Staff Meetings, 1980-1985 (Box 61, Folder 2)
  Agendas and handwritten notes of staff meetings; "Recommended Discipline Policy," Mohonasen Senior High School," and cover letter to Charles Santelli from Harry Lampman, May 19, 1981; Report to the NYSUT Board of Directors from the Committee on the Local Assessment of NYSUT Services 1984-85, 2/11/85
- Staff Meetings, 1983-1987 (Box 61, Folder 3)
  Questionnaires for local presidents; teacher attitude surveys; handwritten notes of staff meetings; agendas for field representatives training sessions
- Staff Training Workshop, 1981 (Box 61, Folder 4)
  January 12-13, 1981. Tentative schedules, January 12 and November 9-10, 1981; evaluation form; list of field staff scheduled to attend; transcript of remarks by Albert Shanker re tuition tax credits, January 13, 1981; handwritten notes
- Staff Training, 1983 (Box 61, Folder 5)
  January 12-13, 1983. Tentative program
- Standards – AFT, 1997 (Box 61, Folder 6)
  Reports by American Federation of Teachers, "Making Standards Better 1977: An Annual Fifty-State Report on Efforts to Raise Academic Standards" (pre-publication copy); "Setting the Stage for High Standards: Elements of Effective School Discipline," 1997; "Reaching High Standards, " 1996; Times Union newspaper clipping, "New York Gets a 'C' On School Standards," 7/29/97
- Standards – Educational Conference Board (ECB) March 4, 1998 (Box 61, Folder 7)
  Agenda of March 4 meeting; financial statement; minutes of February 4 meeting; letters sent to individual regents from ECB chair re report, "The Cost of Higher Standards"; text of report; handwritten personal and confidential note from Carl T. Hayden, chancellor of the Board of Regents, praising report
- Standards – Effective Teaching Program See: Effective Teaching Program -- Standards
- STATE AID / State Budget / School Financing See also: Finance/Financing See also: ECB - State Aid See also: Levittown v. Nyquist See also: Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education See also: Rubin
- State Aid, 1980-1981 (Box 61, Folder 8)
  NYSUT memos analyzing executive budget proposals for aid to elementary and secondary schools
- State Aid – Budget Proposals, 1980-1981 (Box 61, Folder 9)
  NYSUT printed plans: State Aid Proposal 1980-81; State Aid to Public Education 1980-81: Fiscal Problems Facing Public Education: Elementary and Secondary Schools, City University of New York, State University of New York, Community Colleges, February 25, 1980; Selected Indicators of School District Wealth; NYSUT 1980 Legislative Program; New York State Division of the Budget 19880-81 New York State Executive Budget Proposals on State Aid to Public Schools, January 1980
- State Budget, 1978-1979 (Box 61, Folder 10)
  NYSUT publication, "1978-79 State Aid Proposals: Regents Proposal, Executive Budget Proposal, Educational Conference Board Proposal; Individual District Data Alphabetical by County," February 1978; NYSUT Information Bulletins re City University of New York (CUNY) Recommendations in the 1979-80 New York State Executive Budget, for CUNY and SUNY community colleges, and for elementary and secondary public schools, February 1979; suggestions for state aid modifications; letter to state legislators; text of Senate-Assembly bill re state aid to education
- State Budget, 1977-1978 (Box 61, Folder 11)
  The Regents Proposal for Improving State Aid to Public Education in New York State, State Education Department (SED), December 1977; SED letter to NYSUT research director Santelli re inability of SED to provide its publications to all teachers due to lack of funds, February 25, 1977, with text of Commissioner's Regulations re distribution of publications; NYSUT publication, "Education in the 1977-78 Executive Budget"; chart showing Bundy aid to independent colleges and universities, May 1977
- State Budget, 1976-1977 (Box 61, Folder 12)
  State budget director's budget summary, 1976-77; NYSUT research division budget analyses: Brief Synopsis of State Aid for 1976-77; Highlights of the 1976-77 New York State Supplemental Budget; "Education in the 1976-77 Executive Budget: A Preliminary Report to the NYSUT Executive Committee," January 23, 1976
- State Aid, 1981-1982 (Box 61, Folder 13)
  NYSUT analyses
- State Aid, 1982-1983 (Box 61, Folder 14)
  NYSUT documents: State Aid to Public Schools 1982-83; Solutions to Fiscal Problems Facing Public Schools, March 1982; 1982-83 State Aid Proposal of NYSUT/Educational Conference Board: Estimated Operating Aid Increases for Individual School Districts, February 1982; related memos
- State Aid, 1983-1984 (Box 61, Folder 15)
  New York State Division of the Budget Preliminary Description of 1983-84 New York State Aid Programs Funded in General Support for Public Schools Appropriations, March 28, 1983; report from Regents Task Group on State Aid to Public Schools proposing state aid recommendation for 1983-84, with cover letter to Regents from Education Commissioner Gordon Ambach, November 19, 1982; NYSUT Information Bulletin re 1983-84 state aid to public schools
- State Aid, 1979-1980 (Box 61, Folder 16)
  NYSUT analyses, letters to legislators; NYS Division of the Budget 1979-80 Executive Budget Proposals on State Aid to Public Schools; State Education Report, "Providing State Aid for the Education of Handicapped Children Based on a Study of Program Costs: A Report Required by Chapter 786 of the Laws of 1978, Part 2," October 1979
- State Aid, 1988-1989 (Box 61, Folder 17)
  State Education Department "Proposal for Legislative Action in 1988 Concerning State Aid to Schools"; third draft of NYSUT proposal for state aid to public schools, with editing marks, February 23, 1988; aid projections; discussion outline for meeting of Regents with Chairman Salerno and Members of the Temporary Commission on State Aid Distribution, October 6, 1989; related memos
- Governor's Task Force on State Aid (folder 1), 1974-1975 (Box 61, Folder 18)
  "Tax Limiting Equalization," A Preliminary Report to the Task Force on State Aid for Elementary and Secondary Schools, prepared by Senate Education Committee and Institute for Urban Sciences Research at SUNY Stony Brook; task force preliminary report, with press release summarizing recommendations, February 3; press release summarizing final task force recommendations, April 4, 1974; NYS School Boards Association preliminary proposal for 1974 state aid; correspondence; newspaper clippings; handwritten notes
- Governor's Task Force on State Aid (folder 2), 1974-1975 (Box 61, Folder 19)
  Comparative statistics of aid by school district, with cover letter from NYSUT president Tom Hobart, April 5, 1974; spreadsheet for Giufredda tax-limiting equation by district; "Task Force Proposal for 1974 Legislation on State Aid for Elementary and Secondary Schools: Computer Runs"; task force proposal overview; New York State Office for Local Government Memorandum to Local Government Officials, "Exclusion of Pension and Retirement Liabilities from Constitutional Tax Limitations," April 2, 1974
- State Aid – State Documents, 1978-1979 (Box 62, Folder 1)
  Documents from the Education Unit of the New York State Division of the Budget: "Description of New York State Public School Aid Provisions," April 10, 1979; "Description of New York State Public School Aid Changes Approved for 1978-79 School Year," "Measuring the Wealth of School Districts for the Apportionment of Aid to Public Schools in New York State: Full Valuation Vs. Personal Income," August 1978; "Reducing the Variations in Per Pupil Operating Expense Among New York State School Districts by Enlarging the Tax Base: A Regional Tax Base Model," September 1978
- State Aid – NYSUT Documents, 1976-1978 (Box 62, Folder 2)
  NYSUT documents: "Executive Budget Recommendations for 1976-77 State Aid for Elementary and Secondary Schools: Preliminary Estimates (prepared for local presidents)," "Regents Proposal for 1977-78 State Aid to Public Schools: Preliminary Estimates, November 1976," "1978-79 State Aid Proposals: Regents Proposal, Executive Budget Proposal, Educational Conference Board Proposal," individual district data by legislative Senate and Assembly District and alphabetical by county, February 1978
- State Aid – NYSUT Publicity Material (Box 62, Folder 3)
  NYSUT fact sheet and draft mock-up, questions and answers, memos
- State Aid (folder 1), 1978-1979 (Box 62, Folder 4)
  NYSUT lists, "Increases in Operating Aid: Governor's and Educational Conference Board Proposals 1978-79 to 1979-80," comparisons by district and county, February 14, 1979; NYSUT analysis of state aid proposals for elementary and secondary public schools in 1979-80 executive budget, February 1979; State Aid Proposal by Educational Conference Board; Suggestions for Modification of Governors Proposal 1978-79; report, "Regional Differences in Costs: A Study by a Sub-Committee of the Legislative Committee of the New York State Council of School District Administrators, September 1978; letters to local presidents urging members to contact state legislators in support of adequate state aid to public schools, March-April 1979; letter to legislator from NYSUT executive vice president urging support, March 29, 1979
- State Aid (folder 2), 1978-1979 (Box 62, Folder 5)
  Related material
- Temp. State Commission on State Aid (folder 1) (Box 62, Folder 6)
  Meeting minutes; draft position statements; public testimony; budgets and statistics
- Temp. State Commission on State Aid (folder 2) (Box 62, Folder 7)
  Report of the commission, "Funding for Fairness: A Report of the New York State Temporary Commission on the Distribution of State Aid to Local School Districts"
- Temp. State Commission on State Aid (folder 3) (Box 62, Folder 8)
  Correspondence and related materials re distribution of state aid to local school districts
- State Aid (folder 1), 1975-1977 (Box 62, Folder 9)
  Regents and Educational Conference Board 1978-79 Operating Aid Comparisons, December 20, 1977; letter to Regents from Commissioner of Education Gordon Ambach with attached summary of legislative proposal for state aid, October 11, 1977; letter from Ambach to Regents with materials re state aid policy issues, July 20, 1977; Educational Conference Board 1978-79 State Aid Proposal; Regents Proposal for 1977-78 State Aid to Public Schools: Preliminary Estimates (NYSUT document); statement by Dr. Stanley L. Raub, executive director of the New York State School Board Association, Joint Legislative Hearing, Senate Committee on Cities, Assembly Cities Committee, November 30, 1977; letter to Commissioner Ambach from NYSUT president Thomas Hobart commenting on Initial Report of the Regents Task Force on the State Aid Formula, October 14, 1977; summary of report, with cover letter from Ambach to Regents, September 16, 1977; NYSUT briefing paper, 1975-76 State Aid for Education; United Teachers Legislative Program 77, January 6, 1977; NYSUT statistical analyses re trends in state aid to school districts; newspaper clippings; related materials
- State Aid (folder 2), 1975-1977 (Box 62, Folder 10)
  Correspondence and reports as above
- State Aid (folder 3), 1975-1977 (Box 62, Folder 11)
  Plan and Annual Report Requirements for Compliance with the Additional Apportionment Provisions of Chapter 241 of the Laws of 1974, prepared by State Education Department, June 1974; State of New York 1974 Legislation on State Aid for Elementary and Secondary Schools: A Summary, June 1974; related reports, correspondence
- State Aid – Micro-Programs, 1982-1983 (Box 63, Folder 1)
  Technical manuals and articles re PASCAL, BASIC, and other programming languages; computer printouts of lines of code
- State Aid, 1985-1986 (Box 63, Folder 2)
  New York State School Boards Association publications: Overview of 1986 Legislative Action on State Aid to Schools; Summary of 1985-86 New York State School Aid Programs Adopted through State Budget Bills; Comparison among 1985-86 General Support for Public Schools Programs of New York State Legislature (As Enacted on April 5, 1985) Educational Conference Board (Announced on January 14, 1985) and Governor Cuomo's Executive Budget (Released January 22, 1985); NYSUT memos re state aid proposal for teacher salary, other issues; Report of Regents Committee on Administration, Law and Legislation to the Board of Regents, November 13-14, 1985; New York State Educational Conference Board documents: State Aid Proposal for 1986-87; draft Recommendations to Improve Public School Teaching; related documents
- State Aid, 1984-1985 (Box 63, Folder 3)
  "Meeting with Constituent Representatives to Review Proposed State Aid Regulations to be Submitted at the Board of Regents April 26-27, 1984 Meeting," including text of proposed changes re Teacher Resource and Computer Training Centers; agenda for meeting; report, "State Aided Programs: Elementary and Secondary Education, New York State," August 1982, with NYSUT cover memo; similar report, prepared by State Education Department, July 1984; NYSUT memo re ten-year school aid trends, May 11, 1981; comparative statistics with five most populous states; State Education Department Proposals for Legislative Action in 1985 Concerning State Aid to Schools
- State Aid for Public Schools, 1978-1979 (Box 63, Folder 4)
  NYSUT publications: "Reducing the Variations in Per Pupil Operating Expense among New York State School Districts by Enlarging the Tax Base," September 1978; "Measuring the Wealth of School Districts for the Apportionment of Aid to Public Schools in New York State: Full Valuation vs. Personal Income," August 1978; "Understanding Financial Support of Public Schools," 1978-79; 1979-80 Executive Budget Proposals on State Aid to Public Schools, February 23, 1979; Basic Financial Data in Major Operating School Districts in New York State, 1976-77; agenda for meeting of NYSUT Commission on Equitable Public School Funding, March 2-3, 1979; handwritten notes
- School Finance (folder 1), 1973-1979 (Box 63, Folder 5)
  Workbook for NYSUT School Finance and Budget Analysis Workshop, April 13-14, 1977; Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights Under Law "Summary of State-Wide School Finance Cases Since 1973," February 1977; NYSUT publication, "Selected Indicators of School District Wealth," April 27, 1979; related papers, position statements by school districts; memo to NYSUT research director Charles Santelli re political limits to school finance reform (an Urban Institute paper), November 23, 1973
- School Finance (folder 2), 1973-1979 (Box 63, Folder 6)
  Scholarly research papers and reports
- School Finance – California Legal Decision 1974 (Box 63, Folder 7)
  John Serrano, Jr., et al. vs. Ivy Baker Priest, Treasurer of the State of California, et al., memorandum opinion re intended decision, Superior Court of the State of California for the County of Los Angeles, filed April 10, 1974, docket No. 938,254
- National School Finance Conference, 1979 (Box 63, Folder 8)
  January 14-16, 1979. List of tentative topics for discussion; facilitative correspondence
- School Financing – Testimony, 1975-1976 (Box 63, Folder 9)
  Statements by NYSUT president William Hobart and others before the Senate Finance Committee, Regents legislative hearings, and other state and congressional bodies re the need to increase funding to public schools
- NYSUT Commission on Equitable Public School Funding, 1982 (Box 63, Folder 10)
  January 6, 1982. Agenda for meeting of January 6, 1982; list of commission members; decision in appeal of Levittown v. Nyquist, October 26, 1981; charts showing operating aid formulas; Response of Thomas Y. Hobart, Jr., President of the New York State United Teachers, to the Survey-Questionnaire of the Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education
- Basic Minimum Guarantee, 1979 (Box 63, Folder 11)
  c. 1979. Statement by NYSUT president Hobart: "NYSUT Advocates the Use of a Basic Minimum State Aid Guarantee to All Districts"
- Spending Caps, 1979 (Box 63, Folder 12)